A Guide to the Dr. George Chambers Woodson Papers, 1888-1958 (bulk 1920-1936)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Dr. George Chambers Woodson Papers, 1888-1958 (bulk 1920-1936)
The Library of Virginia
41529
.95 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased 4 November 2004.
Biographical Information
George Chambers Woodson was born 23 February 1885 to John and Martha Saunders Woodson of Buckingham County, Virginia. He attended Richmond High School and Medical College of Virginia, graduating in 1907. After his internship at the Richmond City Hospital, 1907-1908, he was associated with Dr. W.H. Parker in general practice at the Chimborazo Sanatorium for the treatment of tuberculosis from 1908 to 1912. He did post graduate work in New York. He married Lillian Burger Woodson and had one son, George Stuart Woodson. Dr. Woodson maintained a practice in Richmond and was a member of the Churchill Medical Society. He died 24 November 1967 and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1888-1958 (bulk 1920-1936) of Dr. George Chambers Woodson documenting his medical practice in Richmond, Virginia, and work with the Churchill Medical Society. Included are account books, birth records, case notes and reports, correspondence, diploma, manuscripts and writings, photographs, publications, and speech notes. Of note are the Physicians Record Book of Births, 1916-1936, which contain 236 recorded births in Richmond, Virginia. Included are ages of mother and father, birthplace, occupation, race, address, date of marriage, and name, place, and time of children's birth.
The case notes and reports include information on the patients medical history, illness and symptoms, treatment and recovery. Included are notes on cases of bronchial asthma, cancer, cardiac disease, dementia, diphtheria, hysteria, morphine addiction, and tape worms in patients. The manuscripts include clinical papers written by Dr. Woodson on a variety of medical topics including acute Bright's disease, bronchial asthma, miscarriages, and the treatment of pneumonia. He also wrote about the effects of some medicines such as digitalis, salicylin, serums, vaccines, and opium. Also included is a copy of the manuscript, "Technique of Contraception," by Dr. James F. Cooper, medical director of the American Birth Control League (later Planned Parenthood).
Also included is an account book, 1939-1958, including personal accounts, taxes, and stock and dividends held. Publications include brochures from Catawba Sanitarium in Roanoke, Virginia, and Clifton Springs Sanitarium in Clifton Springs, New York. Also included are several notes and speeches given to the Churchill Medical Society, 1921-1928, regarding a new hospital proposal, review of previous year's work of the organization, and the welfare of constituents.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Account book, Part 1, 1939-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Account book, Part 2 1939-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bible (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Blank forms, Nd (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Case file, Cancer of the lung, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Case notes, Bowel obstruction, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Case notes, Fatal case of diphtheria, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Case notes, Hysteria, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Case notes, Medical cases, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Case notes, Sulphur internally, Nd (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Case notes, Tape worm in a child, Nd (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Case notes, Two cases of serum, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Case notes, Unknown, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Case reports, Case of bronchial asthma, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Case reports, Case of bronchial asthma, Nd (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Case reports, Case of cardiac, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Case reports, Case of dementia praecox (catatonic type), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Case reports, Morphine addiction, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Hermitage Country Club, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- History of Churchill, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- List of medical societies in Virginia, Nd (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Medical College of Virginia, Anniversary button, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Manuscripts, Acute Bright's Disease, Nd (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Manuscripts, Case of Bronchial Asthma, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Manuscripts, Case of Digitalis, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Manuscripts, Case of Pathylogical Labor of Mother, Nd (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Manuscripts, General Considerations Regarding Serum and Vaccine Therapy, Nd (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Manuscripts, The Management of Abortion, Nd (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Manuscripts, Opium, Its Uses and Abuses, Nd (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Manuscripts, Salicylin and Salicylates in Medicine, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Manuscripts, Treatment of Pneumonia, Nd (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Manuscripts, Technique of Contraception, by Dr. James F. Cooper, Nd (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Photographs, c. 1930-1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Physicians Record Book of Births, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Physicians Record Book of Births, 1921-1923 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Physicians Record Book of Births, 1924-1931 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Physicians Record Book of Births, 1932-1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Publications, American Journal of Public Health, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Publications, Bulletin of Academy of Medicine of Cleveland, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Publications, Catawba Sanatorium (Roanoke, VA) brochure, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Publications, Clifton Springs (NY) Sanitarium brochure, c. 1940 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Publications, Clinic Excerpts, Vol. 2 No. 3, c. 1930 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Publications, Virginia Medical Monthly, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Publications, Virginia Medical Monthly, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Publications, What We Eat and Why, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- St. James Church (Richmond, VA), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Speech notes, Churchill Medical Society, 1921-1928 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- University of Richmond, Report cards, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Diploma, University College of Medicine, 1907 (Folder Oversize folder on shelf)
- RESTRICTED UNTIL 2064 (Box 3)